<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nevves from France. A true relation of the great losses which happened by the lamentable accident of fire in the citie of Paris, the 24. day of October last past, 1621 which burnt downe the Merchants Bridge, the Changers Bridge, and diuers houses neere vnto them. Together with the speedy diligence vsed by the Duke De Monbason, gouernour of the said towne, for the quenching thereof. Also a decree made in the Court of Parliament in Paris, whereby an order is taken for prouiding for the merchants that haue lost their goods by the sayd fire, and to preuent the like mischance in time to come. Translated according to the French copie, printed at Paris.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11279.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102578</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838350</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838350</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2725</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01164)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2725)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1023:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nevves from France. A true relation of the great losses which happened by the lamentable accident of fire in the citie of Paris, the 24. day of October last past, 1621 which burnt downe the Merchants Bridge, the Changers Bridge, and diuers houses neere vnto them. Together with the speedy diligence vsed by the Duke De Monbason, gouernour of the said towne, for the quenching thereof. Also a decree made in the Court of Parliament in Paris, whereby an order is taken for prouiding for the merchants that haue lost their goods by the sayd fire, and to preuent the like mischance in time to come. Translated according to the French copie, printed at Paris.</title>
                  <author>France. Parlement (Paris). Proceedings. 1621-10-26.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Purslowe] for R. R[ounthwaite] at the Golden Lyon in Paules Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Original French title not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and bookseller's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11282 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fires --  France --  Paris --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Paris (France) --  History --  Louis XIII, 1610-1643.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2725:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:2725:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 57 -->
            <head>NEWES FROM FRANCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD, whoſe goodneſſe and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie is incomprehenſible, to our humane thoughts and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, doth not alwayes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the arrowes of his wrath vpon miſerable ſinners; who by the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableneſſe of their offences, haue ſtirred vp and prouoked his wrath againſt them, becauſe he deſireth not the death of a ſinner, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he ſhould conuert and be ſaued: But when he ſeeth that they waxe worſe, and are hardened in their ſinnes, and lull themſelues aſleepe in humane delights: Then he rouzeth vp himſelfe with the ſcourge of aduerſitie, and diſchargeth the furie of his wrath againſt them, to make them turne vnto him, who is the Soueraigne Ruler, of whome they hold their being, and all their power. Then (I ſay) he employeth the great forces of the heauens,
<pb facs="tcp:2725:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->and the Elements, thereby to heale the vlcer of their vices, that wallow and take pleaſure in ſinne, as a Sow delighteth to wallow in the mire.</p>
            <p>Which plainely appeareth by the deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble accident happened of late in the Citie of <hi>Paris,</hi> where the force and furie of fire ſtrucke ſuch an aſtoniſhment in all the inhabitants, that they thought the Towne, like a ſecond <hi>Sodome,</hi> would ſuddenly haue beene conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to aſhes, by the impetuous flames of fire that threatned them; and yet could not truely know the truth how it began: For it is ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly reported, that men cannot aſſuredly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare any truth thereof: And it is prohibited by a Decree made in Court of Parliament, in any ſort to ſpeake thereof, to ſhunne and auoid the tumult and commotion of the people. But ſo it is, that vpon Saturday the 23. of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, about one of the clocke after midnight, the fire began in ſuch manner to flame out vpon the Merchants Bridge, that the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof were ſurprized ſleeping in their beds, before they heard or perceiued it: for the fire (which met with nothing elſe but that which was combuſtible) increaſed with ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:2725:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 58 -->impetuoſitie, that in a ſhort time, all the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that ſtood vpon the ſaid Bridge on both ſides, were on fire, by meanes of certaine beames that lay croſſe ouer one to another.</p>
            <p>The Change Bridge did no leſſe feele the force and vigour which the ſaid fire vomited out, by meanes of the flames iſſuing from the ſame: for that deſcending downe to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations thereof, in the end it burnt and caſt it into the water, with all the houſes ſtanding thereon, together with the great riches of the inhabitants, that by no meanes could ſaue any thing thereof, by reaſon of the ſmoake and heate, that hurt and choked diuers of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſome men that were burnt, fell down with the beames and peeces of wood all bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into the riuer.</p>
            <p>You may iudge how many children and poore innocent ſoules were buried in that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piteous fire, for that their fathers and mothers had worke enough to doe, to ſaue themſelues. Many women newly brought in bed, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that were ſicke in their beds, payd that debt to nature, which all of vs one day muſt doe, neither hauing that force nor dexteritie ſufficient to ſaue themſelues. It was moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable
<pb facs="tcp:2725:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->to heare the wofull cries and ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, not onely of thoſe that were afflicted, but alſo of the ſpectators of that miſerable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident: The men in great feare ſaued them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from that vnexpected deluge, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner halfe dead, blaming the heauens for their diſaſter, and not knowing how to bee reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for their loſſe, tooke reuenge vpon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; and men were as much troubled to comfort them, as to ſaue the reſt of thoſe that were within their houſes. Women in extreme diſcomfort, their haire hanging about their heades, and in a manner naked, beholding that horrible ſpectacle, bathing their faces with teares, and caſting a thouſand ſighes vp into the ayre, ſwouned, and in a manner fell into deſpaire. Diuers ſeruants, both maides and men, as well as their maſters and miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, induring and feeling the rigor of that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, ſtood in the like manner as others did, ready to pay their debt to cruell deſtiny.</p>
            <p>The fire ſtill waxing greater and greater, mounted vp into the ayre with mighty flames, and caſt ſuch and ſo great a light ouer all the Citie, that thoſe which knew nothing of that vnfortunate miſchance, being awaked
<pb facs="tcp:2725:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 59 -->by the popular rumour, were in a maze, to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine from whence that light ſhould come, not knowing the cauſe; but as others did, in great feare ranne vnto the place.</p>
            <p>The Bels in diuers Churches began to ring, the noyſe whereof aſtoniſhing diuers Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of the ſayd Towne, cauſed them to arme themſelues: at which time <hi>Paris</hi> began to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a great tumult. When the Duke <hi>de Monbaſon,</hi> Gouernour of the City, hauing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence thereof, came vnto the place with his Company of ſouldiers, the Watch, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others; all in Armes, placing a Court of guard at both ends of the Bridges, and other places. From thence he went to poſſeſſe the ſtrongeſt and moſt eminent places, as the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtille,</hi> the Kings Court called the <hi>Louure,</hi> the Towne houſe, and diuers places of note; which done, he cauſed fires to be made tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout all the Citie, and Lanternes to bee hung out of euery window, in ſo great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, that it was as light as at noone-day: and cauſed foure Culuerins to be brought to both the ends of the ſaid Bridges: and to conclude, vſed ſuch diligence in that imminent danger, ſtill keeping good watch, doubting ſome
<pb facs="tcp:2725:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->treaſon, that he is perpetually to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, while he was thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently buſied about that publike care, ſo neceſſary in ſuch an extremitie: The fire, that like a tempeſt, deuoured and ſpoyled all that it tooke hold on, was not content with that whereon it had firſt ſeized, but hauing ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the greedie deſire thereof, and brought all the houſes and dwelling places vpon the ſayd two Bridges, into vtter ruine and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and layd them in the valley of miſerie, encreaſed more and more, and carried her flames into the Galue place; and if it had not beene for ſome artificiall trenches, and mens helpe, who in great numbers ranne thither, the great Caſtle, and the gate of <hi>Paris,</hi> was in danger to haue felt the furie thereof. On the other ſide, in the extremitie of the raging flames, at the other end of the Bridges afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, the fire was no leſſe furious: for hauing ſeized vpon all the houſes and ſhops neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, as farre as before the Pallace, it tooke hold on the Dyall, and beganne to melt the Lead that couered it, vntill a great number of nimble and couragious men, ran thither, and
<pb facs="tcp:2725:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 60 -->employed all their forces and induſtries, to ſaue that admirable worke.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>de Monbaſon,</hi> while euery man was buſied about that pitifull and moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table buſines, on Sunday in the morning, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed commandement to bee made by ſound of Trumpet, that all the Citizens ſhould fill and ſet diuers tubs full of water at all the corners of the ſtreetes. And it is an incredible thing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, how great a number of people from all places ranne vnto that place, to ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the ſight of that horrible fire, which filled their eyes with teares, and their breſts with ſighes.</p>
            <p>This (friendly Reader) in briefe is the true relation that I can make vnto thee, to let thee know and vnderſtand this lamentable action: from whence the ſame proceeded no man knowes. Neuertheleſſe, the Court, by a Decree made the 25. day of Octob. hath commanded all Iudges and Officers to make an exact enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of thoſe, that wickedly haue committed that diſorder; and that the knowledge thereof being had, ſo good Iuſtice may be vſed therein, that ſuch as they may take example thereby.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:2725:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
               <head>
                  <hi>A Decree made by the Court of</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in PARIS, whereby Order is taken <hi>for prouiding for the Merchants, that haue</hi> loſt their goods by the ſaid fire, and to preuent the like miſchance in time to come.</head>
               <p>VPon the Declaration made by the Kings Atturney General, touching the fire hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by night, betweene Saturday and Sunday, the 24. of this moneth of October, which burnt and conſumed the Changers and the Merchants Bridges, and ſome houſes neere vnto them, as well on the Palace ſide, vnto the Leather ſtreet, as on the great Caſtle ſide, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring, That the Court would be pleaſed, to giue him Commiſſion to make information of the beginning of that fire, conſidering the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers reports that were ſpred abroad in the Towne, that might bee a meanes to procure great trouble in the ſame, and to make ſpeedie prouiſion for the neceſſitie of thoſe, that haue loſt their goods by the ſaid Fire, as alſo that the like inconuenience may not happen. After the Lieutenant ciuill, and the ſubſtitute of the ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:2725:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->Atturney generall had audience, being for that cauſe ſent for, vpon information that they had begunne to make inquirie thereof.</p>
               <p>The Court hath enjoyned and enioyneth the Prouoſt of <hi>Paris,</hi> or his Lieutenants ciuill or cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall, diligently to continue the information by them begun, touching the originall of that Fire, and to make and finiſh the inditement of the authours of the ſame, and their adherents, ready for the definitiue ſentence, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any oppoſitions, or appeales whatſoeuer: and to the Subſtitute of the ſayd Atturney gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to be aſſiſtant vnto them, and with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to certifie this Court thereof. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, expreſſely command and prohibite (vpon paine of death) all perſons, of what qualities or conditions ſoeuer they be, to aſſemble toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther either by day or by night, vnleſſe it bee by commandement of the Magiſtrate, nor yet to miſ behaue themſelues by words, nor to vſe any reproches, vnder pretence of diuerſitie of Religions, or to ſow or caſt foorth any bruites or rumours touching the inconuenience of the ſayd Fire, tending to the diſquietneſſe of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; but to liue peaceably and quietly, vnder the Kings Authority and Edicts. Commanding
<pb facs="tcp:2725:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->all vagrant perſons, and men that are of lewde conuerſation, liuing idlely, preſently, without any delay, to depart out of the Citie, after the publication of theſe preſents: And their Oaſts, and ſuch as harbour them, to diſcloſe them, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine perſonally to anſwere for them: And to prouide for the neceſſitie and reliefe of the poore inhabitants, vtterly vndone and begge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the ſayd Fire: Humble ſupplication ſhall be made vnto the King, to be pleaſed to beſtow His gracious liberalitie vpon them. And in the meane time it is ordeined, That the ſaid Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney generall ſhall make a note of the names of thoſe, that haue endured the ſaid loſſes; and what trades and occupations they were of, as alſo of the number of their children and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, who may be put into Saint <hi>Louis</hi> Houſe, there to be lodged and nouriſhed for the ſpace of ſixe moneths: and to that end, there ſhall be ten thouſand Frankes put into the hands of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot</hi> and <hi>Sainctot,</hi> Ouerſeers of the Hoſpitall. And further, that gatherings ſhall be made through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Pariſhes of this Citie, to ayde the ſaid diſtreſſed people. And to that end, the people ſhall be exhorted by the Vicars: and Officers of the ſayd Pariſhes, to appoint certaine perſons of
<pb facs="tcp:2725:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->good qualitie, from month to month, to make the ſayd Gatherings. Commanding the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſt of Merchants and Sheriffes, to ſet men on worke continually, to take vp, and rid away the ruines of the ſaid Fire fallen into the water, that the courſe of the ſame may not be hindred, and to make it nauigable: and in the meane time, to appoint honeſt men of good credit, and well experienced, for the ſpace of a whole yeere, to ſearch in the bottome of the water, for the goods and merchandizes, that ſhall be found to haue beene drowned; and the ſame to bee brought into the common Hoſpitall of the ſaid Citie; whereof an Inuentorie ſhall bee made by one of the ſayd Sheriffes, that they may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the owners thereof. And alſo that all Boatmen, and ſuch as vſe to ſaile vp and downe the riuer; and all others, that ſhall haue found any thing of the ſame, to bring them to the ſaid Hoſpitall of the Towne, and to bring a certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thereof, vpon paine of hanging. We like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe command the Prouoſt of Merchants, and the Sheriffes, to keepe and hold within the ſayd Hoſpitall of the Towne, and the Towne-houſe, as alſo in euery Ward, ſuch a quantity of hooks,
<pb facs="tcp:2725:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->buckets of lether, and other ſuch neceſſaries as ſhall be needfull in time to come, to ſerue for ſuch inconueniences of Fire, and to certifie the ſame vnto the Clerke of the ſaid Court. And the Captaine of the Watch, to keepe good watch by night in the Palace, and other vſuall places. And to the end, in time to come, that the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Fire may not take in the Palace, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſhoppes that are built vp againſt the ſame, We ordeine and command, that the new ſhops built from the Dyall Tower, to the bail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liage Gate, on the Quay-ſide of the riuer, ſhall be pulled downe; and none of them to be built vp againe for any cauſe or reaſon whatſoeuer. And further, that all Proceſſes ſued out againſt the bodies of thoſe that dwelt vpon the ſayd Bridges, by reaſon of any Obligations, Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or Arreſts, in what manner ſoeuer they be done, ſhall ſurceaſe for the ſpace of a yeere: and that by the ordinarie Iudges there ſhall bee ſufficient delay made, conſidering their loſſe; and whatſoeuer ſhall by them bee ordeined, to be put in execution; notwithſtanding any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions or appeales whatſoeuer. And this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Decree ſhall, by the diligence of the Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb facs="tcp:2725:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->generall, bee publiſhed, as well in the Church Porches, as openly by ſound of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and ſet vp vpon the corners of the ſtreetes.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Giuen in the Parliament <date>the 26. of October. 1621.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Signed <hi>Du Tillet.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
